<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/categories/mobile/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.maciejmroz.com/categories/mobile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the era of dedicated gaming devices coming to an end?</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Today was the day when PlayStation Vita launched worldwide. I had the chance to play most of the launch games already during GDC Europe last August and I think that both hardware and launch lineup are impressive. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy PS Vita on launch. It&amp;rsquo;s probably a very sad day for Sony, bacause &amp;ldquo;PlayStation&amp;rdquo; is my religion (on Facebook, at least :) ).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What happended? I faced the truth - mainstream mobile gaming is already on Android and iOS, and a lot of titles are released every day. I know that every single developer out there is working on these platforms, and they don&amp;rsquo;t mind selling the game for $1-$5. You can&amp;rsquo;t possibly deny the trends - these devices are the new player in the console market. Just a few months ago I have written (on this blog) that there&amp;rsquo;s not much danger to Vita from the iOS/Android camp. I hate to admit that, but I might have been wrong. Yes, phones and tablets might lose on overall experience, but at the same time they win hands down when it goes to price and convenience. I actually found myself playing games on both iPhone and iPad in past six months or so. And I enjoyed doing it, at least for a short while.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course it doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean Vita is dead on arrival. It&amp;rsquo;s the best portable gaming device Sony (or anyone) could possibly make and a lot of people will buy it. But they will be the most hardcore of the hardcore gamers. Others will settle for the simple and easy solution, sometimes even being fully aware of what they are sacrificing - it all really comes down to the added value. Some cannibalization is bound to happen. Will the remaining group of true gamers be big enough to make PS Vita a viable platform for developers? I hope so. I actually hope that PS Vita will sell a lot more than PSP. If not, we&amp;rsquo;ll end up with a platform that has 2-3 good releases a year &amp;hellip; and that&amp;rsquo;s my biggest fear. You don&amp;rsquo;t buy console at launch because of the launch titles only. You buy the console because of the future games. Lots of them. And I am not sure they are coming :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a gamer I want truly epic experiences. PS Vita has the potential to provide them, potential that might be lost because of where the game industry is going. We are going towards simpler and shallower games, towards replacing challenge with compulsion loops, and towards freemium as a dominating business model &amp;hellip; where&amp;rsquo;s &lt;strong&gt;epic&lt;/strong&gt; in that?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on the mobile revolution</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;People keep talking about &amp;ldquo;mobile&amp;rdquo;, how it&amp;rsquo;s going to be very important (i.e. &amp;ldquo;we have &lt;strong&gt;mobile first&lt;/strong&gt; policy&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip;) but recently it really struck me: most talking about mobile revolution have abolutely no idea. They just don&amp;rsquo;t get it. Which is a bit sad, actually, especially if you think that big media companies are still struggling to make sense of what to do with classic, web-based Internet. Mobile is a revolution can only be understood by mobile users. I remember when CEO of Bigpoint was talking on GDC Europe more than a year ago about buying everyone in his company an iPad. At that time I only thought &amp;ldquo;it&amp;rsquo;s nice&amp;rdquo;. But it was much more than that. It was an investment to create competitive advantage (and a very, very high ROI investment). There&amp;rsquo;s absolutely no way to understand smartphones, tablets and their features without actually using these things. Because it is &lt;strong&gt;that&lt;/strong&gt; disruptive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without previously experiencing these devices, one might believe that correct way of &amp;ldquo;going mobile&amp;rdquo; is to adjust user interface to fit on smaller screen, and ship. It&amp;rsquo;s great recipe for failure. Fitting existing content and PC-like user experience into something that is completely different? It cannot be made to work. It&amp;rsquo;s about entire user experience! Look at the usage pattern of mobile devices. When I pick up the phone, I want to something &lt;strong&gt;very specific, right now&lt;/strong&gt;. More often than not it is not my primary activity, so I don&amp;rsquo;t intend to waste too much time doing it. The thinking part is already behind me, now I am at the &amp;ldquo;doing&amp;rdquo; stage. This &amp;ldquo;right now&amp;rdquo; flow starts actually even before developer has any chance to interact with the user - it happens when an application is launched. Launching a web browser, going to website, and then doing something is just taking too long. It&amp;rsquo;s one the reasons we are seeing the &amp;ldquo;applification&amp;rdquo; of Internet (which is very interesting trend on its own, and it&amp;rsquo;s the very reason Google cannot afford to fail with Android).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;ldquo;There&amp;rsquo;s an app for that&amp;rdquo; is more than just a slogan - it&amp;rsquo;s the very definition of what is happening and what is expected. If you are interested about other driving forces behind the switch to dedicated applications, see &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BiYNs5uPPEE&#34;&gt;this video&lt;/a&gt; [youtube.com]. I have said it a few times (although not on the Internet) when talking about usability of social games: treat all your users as if they have ADHD. If an user has to wonder &amp;ldquo;what next?&amp;rdquo; it is the user you just lost. This is even more true on mobile. Not only for games, but for everything the users might possibly want to do. Their time is limited. Everything that saves time is good, everything that wastes time is bad. Simple, isn&amp;rsquo;t it? Yes, but it&amp;rsquo;s impossible to achieve if you are not obsessed about usability. Give him/her an app to do just one thing, and make it as easy and user friendly as possible. &lt;strong&gt;Nothing&lt;/strong&gt; more. If you don&amp;rsquo;t, you will lose that user, because someone else will do it the right way. This is why Facebook has dedicated Messenger app - it&amp;rsquo;s one app to do just one thing. If Facebook didn&amp;rsquo;t do this app, somebody else would. Feature creep is simply something you cannot afford. While most of the industries get away with one or two extra features without much harm, in mobile, if you are not focused, you are dead. There is no &amp;ldquo;one app to rule them all&amp;rdquo; and there will never be one. But it is still a viable strategy to go mobile with unique content and make money this way, correct? Yes and no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funnily, answer to that doesn&amp;rsquo;t have much to do with mobile computing, more with digital age in general. The problem is simple: content (any content!) is becoming a commodity, because it grows faster than our ability to consume it, and it never disappears. This makes competing on content increasingly difficult - because you have to compete on quality, which in long term leads to a dead end. It applies to music, movies, games, stock photos, etc etc. This is just another disruption that is happening in parallell. Let&amp;rsquo;s go back to mobile devices. Is there a way to succeed there? Of course there is, but the answer is not what everyone would like to hear. Because we are talking about typical disruption as defined in the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.amazon.com/Innovators-Dilemma-Technologies-Cause-ebook/dp/B004OC07GM/ref=sr_1_4?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1325951575&amp;amp;sr=8-4&#34;&gt;Innovator&amp;rsquo;s Dillemma&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;actually, more than one at the same time&#34;&gt;amazon.com&lt;/a&gt; what goes below has to be a guessing game. I might put some references to gaming industry, because that&amp;rsquo;s what I do, but I believe these guesses/conclusions to be quite general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, traditional business models are most likely not going to work, at least not long-term. Freemium is probably the way to go but I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t be suprised to see it evolve into something else. It&amp;rsquo;s already visible in the app stores - statistically paid iOS games are losing money. This is not going to change, and it&amp;rsquo;s happening not because of piracy, but because apps are a commodity. I see a potential for true virtual economy somewhere down the line, but trying to predict how it&amp;rsquo;s going to look like is going into science fiction area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, there&amp;rsquo;s a lot of value in being cross platform and syncing everything &amp;ldquo;in the cloud&amp;rdquo;. You can&amp;rsquo;t just make iOS app. You may (correctly, at the time I am writing this post) believe that iOS devices are the best, but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t really matter. You have to have Android version, and not only Android version - there&amp;rsquo;s also Windows Phone, and two major desktop operating systems. Yes, desktops will be transformed, too. Think for a while what is the reason for success of Evernote or DropBox. If there is collaboration between people, there&amp;rsquo;s no guarantee of homogeneous platform. For some services it&amp;rsquo;s not about losing part of the market - it&amp;rsquo;s about losing the entire market. This is also the reason why mobile cannot be simply ignored.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Advertising will be transformed, but it will not happen very soon. I see a lot of change here, but in a bit longer term. Advertising industry in general is very static. That has a lot to do with how budgets are allocated and how results are measured. In short term, we&amp;rsquo;ll see ad-supported apps as a viable and popular business model - used instead, or in connection with freemium. That brings us to the next point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User engagement is the absolute king. I know I just made a full circle, but it&amp;rsquo;s very important: people have to want to use whatever is offered to them. It&amp;rsquo;s not enough that they try it - they have to like it enough to go back, and refer it to their friends. And if we add the shift in business models it becomes obvious that in order to succeed the change of thinking is required. Instead of &amp;ldquo;How we are going to make money on it?&amp;rdquo; it&amp;rsquo;s time to start asking &amp;ldquo;If we do this project, is it making people lives better?&amp;rdquo;. Thinking outside the box matters more than ever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There will be a lot of failures, and a lot of success stories. It will be very hard, if not impossible, to predict which one is which before actually building it and trying it out with the users. There&amp;rsquo;s absolutely no point in market research because there&amp;rsquo;s no market to research - it doesn&amp;rsquo;t exist yet. Most important of all, as it progresses, mobile revolution will be even more &lt;strong&gt;exciting&lt;/strong&gt; :)&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Onswipe - entering the era of tablet publishing</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/01/04/onswipe-entering-the-era-of-tablet-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/01/04/onswipe-entering-the-era-of-tablet-publishing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Classic web is dying, even if slowly. I will write longer post about that soon. In the meantime, try to use Flipboard for a while … and you will notice that classic portals/blogs are just dinosaurs. They might not know it yet but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the facts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are using WordPress, there is a cure called &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.onswipe.com&#34;&gt;Onswipe&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s not perfect (in fact it is buggy as hell) but shows a lot of promise. Onswipe is a WordPress plugin that provides Flipboard-like experience on an IPad using HTML5. Enter this blog from an iPad, and you will enter completely different world. I suppose it should also work on Android tablets, after all it&amp;rsquo;s just HTML. Onswipe is interesting for two resons. The first reason (and the reason for it&amp;rsquo;s existence) is that it essentially changes website into an &lt;strong&gt;application&lt;/strong&gt;. The second reason it is interesting is because these guys got &lt;a href=&#34;http://venturebeat.com/2011/06/03/onswipe-funding/&#34;&gt;$5M in funding&lt;/a&gt; to write a WordPress plugin :) Which leads to following conclusions:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;There might be another bubble forming, this time around anything with &amp;ldquo;mobile&amp;rdquo; in name&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I live in a wrong country :)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it time to try an Adroid phone now?</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2011/05/08/is-it-time-to-try-an-adroid-phone-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2011/05/08/is-it-time-to-try-an-adroid-phone-now/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve been an IPhone user for loong time. While I did not own the &amp;ldquo;1G&amp;rdquo;, I have my 3G for more than two years now. And, to be honest, it begins to show its age. For quite some time, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting any of the new cool stuff in iOS, and iOS version 4 actually should have never been released on iPhone 3G because it makes a lot of stuff run noticeably slower. So, the question is whether to upgrade to iPhone 4.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest advantages of the iPhone right now are: retina display and iOS (again, I believe that it is the best mobile system out there right now). But the rest of the world wasn&amp;rsquo;t in standstill during the past two years. There are Android based phones that at least on paper look better than iPhone 4 (except for the display, nothing out there can really match it) - fast dual core CPU, more memory, better GPU, better camera, comparable internal flash memory, Flash Player support, NFC chip &amp;hellip; iPhone 4 has none of these, and is more expensive. It also is a very safe choice and an upgrade in every way possible over the iPhone 3G I am using right now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The truth is, I am very &lt;strong&gt;used to&lt;/strong&gt; iOS. I just like it. At the same time I know that buying iPhone 4 right now might not be the best choice. Waiting for iPhone 5 is an option (it will surely feature A5 chip), but seeing the paper-only availability of iPad 2, it&amp;rsquo;s not very optimistic wait. Even assuming that paper launch will be in June, real availability will be probably in September, and possibly later here in Poland. And that&amp;rsquo;s assuming Apple would actually launch it in June. By the way, iPad 2 is officially available for more than a month right now in Poland - but good luck buying one at official Apple reseller. They still have waiting list on the damn thing :(&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, in case of a phone, there&amp;rsquo;s strong possibility of defecting towards Android camp. Not because I want to, but because Apple might not deliver on time. In case I would go for an Adroid device, the new problem arises. Which one?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What to expect from iPad 2</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2011/01/20/what-to-expect-from-ipad-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2011/01/20/what-to-expect-from-ipad-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Before CES, I&amp;rsquo;d say &amp;ldquo;not much&amp;rdquo;. The thing is, today Apple owns the tablet market (if defined as dedicated hardware running dedicated OS), there is almost no competition out there. But it is on the horizon. Take Motorola Xoom as an example. Hardware specs are way beyond iPad 1.0, and if Android 3.0 is going to be that good as people claim, Apple is going to be in real trouble if they release underpowered device. And there will be more and more Android tablets as we go deeper into 2011 &amp;hellip; My guesses for iPad 2 are: SD card slot, front facing camera, and 1GB of RAM. SD card slot is fairly cheap way to greatly improve the device, and is very much in line with intended use - something that would replace laptop for basic photo management tasks. Front facing camera - not much point to discuss. Memory is more interesting - a month ago I&amp;rsquo;d bet on 512 MB, exactly the same as in iPhone 4. But after CES it just sounds cheap and limited. Apple has tradition of selling as little as they can for as much as possible, but I don&amp;rsquo;t really think they can get away with that. I think this is very moderate spec that should be considered basis for more. Retina display? Dual core CPU? Faster GPU? USB slot? They need another iPhone 4, and this time without the antennagate. Right now, after CES, anything is possible.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple Tablet</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2010/02/06/apple-ipad-first-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2010 11:52:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2010/02/06/apple-ipad-first-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Apple tablet is no longer a mystery. The question now is whether it meets the expectations or fits any real needs :) Basically it is an oversized iPhone - 1024x768 multitouch display, 16-64 GB of flash memory, 1 GHz custom CPU, WiFi, Bluetooth etc, and it runs iPhone OS. I already have an iPhone. Is iPad going to perform better enough to justify buying additional device?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;GMail support with push in the iPhone is most of the time sufficient for me. I rarely reply to mails directly from my iPhone, though. If something requires longer answer I usually just use normal computer for that. iPads bigger screen (and bigger virtual keyboard as a result) will surely improve experience here. I can actually imagine writing emails using this thing. Web browsing is where iPad is going to be a lot better than iPhone simply because of screen size and CPU performance (one of the things I noticed immediately at Apple videos is how smooth it runs, it&amp;rsquo;s super fast!). Web and mail if work well might alone be a selling point for people who don&amp;rsquo;t keep &lt;sup&gt;24&lt;/sup&gt;&amp;frasl;&lt;sub&gt;7&lt;/sub&gt; computer at home and actually do turn it on and off. In that scenario iPad is going to be very useful, offering browsing and mail experience very close to &amp;ldquo;full&amp;rdquo; but with instant access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iTunes for music/video/podcasts is nice for people living in the US, I imagine. Apple still has not fully acknowledged existence of Poland, so for me this functionality is not very attractive, simply because it does not work. Of course I can transcode videos and use MP3 for music but that&amp;rsquo;s hardly the experience it should be. For watching video I don&amp;rsquo;t think it can realistically beat big LCD TV, I know that there are some VGA/composite adapters (sold separately), but what I&amp;rsquo;d really like to see is just HDMI output. Or perhaps built in DLNA media server? Both would solve the problem of &amp;ldquo;how to put it on large screen&amp;rdquo;, second one is wireless, which in my dictionary is almost the same as &amp;ldquo;better&amp;rdquo; :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Photo functionality is nice but crippled at the very beginning by the hardware - iPad does not have SD card slot nor USB port. What may be the most attractive usage is loading the photos directly from my camera into the iPad, tag them, rate, sort, delete ones I don&amp;rsquo;t like, upload to Facebook etc. It will be possible but will require additional &amp;ldquo;camera connection kit&amp;rdquo;. Not including these ports by default it strange to say the least. Perhaps they are already planning revised hardware version late this year, and that&amp;rsquo;s just sinister plan to make people buy new hardware in longer term :). Anyway, I really do see the potential here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;iBookstore was obviously going to happen - and I think it is very good it did. It will put a lot of pressure on ebook reader market. I am not entirely convinced on using active IPS display for reading, in the end it is not that much different from staring at the lamp for a long time. Theoretically e-ink displays have an advantage here, and if you try using iRex Iliad (for example) then yes, its display technology is awesome in terms of ease of reading. At the same time, everything else is far from great. Iliad is slow, takes ages to start up, and again ages to load large pdf files, page turning is sluggish, battery life is not so great, and overall user interface is far from easy to navigate. If Apple really can get 10 hours of battery life from iPad (and one month of standby!), while running active high resolution color display, it clearly shows that there is something wrong with all ebook readers released to market so far. This really reminds me of what Apple did to cell phone market. Perhaps they did not built perfect device but still managed to do something better than everyone else. Again, I see a lot of potential here. I&amp;rsquo;d really like to buy books in electronic rather than physical form, but I guess there&amp;rsquo;s long time before that really happens. What is needed is immediate availability of electronic version along with print release, and availability of electronic version of every single book out there. None of these is happening today, probably not even in the US. We&amp;rsquo;ll get there in a few years. Printing industry is insanely wasteful and while I do not care about the environment that much in general, when I can do something environmentally friendly and convenient at the same time - I am all for it. For now, I only want to know if I can upload pdf files directly to the iPad - I might not be able to use it to read commercial books, but there surely is tons of technical documentation, presentations etc that I might want to read on the iPad.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One glaring omission I think everyone considered almost a given before iPad announcement is front facing camera. It means no video conferencing. Perhaps it has something to do with unlimited 3G data plans Apple and AT&amp;T; are offering in the US? Anyway I do see it as a shortcoming, and something surely to be corrected in future hardware release (and everyone will go and buy themselves a new iPad &amp;hellip; Apple is thinking long term here :) ). Network connectivity is where it manages to do very well. 802.11n + Bluetooth 2.1 is very good, built in 3G modem is also nice. There&amp;rsquo;s nothing more to want here. I&amp;rsquo;d only like to know if I can use iPhone as Bluetooth modem for non-3G iPad. The price difference between 3G and non-3G versions is significant and I can&amp;rsquo;t really imagine scenario when I am mobile and without my phone. So why two SIM cards? Seems logical that in this case I should simply be able to go with WiFi-only version.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apple did not forget about productivity apps, and I am sure there will be more with time. However this is where you really need multitasking. iWork applications are ok, but in reality you are switching between these apps and email/web/skype/calculator/pdf reader etc. Non to mention listening to music in background. Which means we are left with very basic functionality. That can be fixed with OS update, at the cost of battery life (which Apple seems to be defending very aggressively). In the end, iPad is no replacement for a laptop or PC/Mac, although to be fair I have to say that it does not try to be one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The idea of doing simple tasks on simple device leads me to another question: do people still need a PC/laptop? Think about it: typical people mostly consume media, what they produce (outside of work) is rather simplistic: photos, videos, some blog posts. They also need basic calendar/todo list, perhaps money management application. Add to this the trend of moving more and more online and running it inside a web browser (obviously a model supported by iPad) and we are soon approaching the world where all of typical stuff people do can be done using one simple device, probably looking a lot like the iPad. I believe it indeed is a new device category, that takes away some of the tasks we so far are used to do on personal computer. I see very strong analogy to game consoles here, btw. I do not play typical &amp;ldquo;3D&amp;rdquo; games on my computer any more. Sure I&amp;rsquo;ll use it to play Civilization, but for most games the console is just better. It&amp;rsquo;s likely going to be the same with iPad, but this time what&amp;rsquo;s left of the personal computer may no longer be necessary for many people.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>