<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Mobile on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</title>
    <link>https://maciejmroz.com/categories/mobile/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Mobile on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://maciejmroz.com/categories/mobile/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Is the era of dedicated gaming devices coming to an end?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>Today was the day when PlayStation Vita launched worldwide. I had the chance to play most of the launch games already during GDC Europe last August and I think that both hardware and launch lineup are impressive. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy PS Vita on launch. It&amp;rsquo;s probably a very sad day for Sony, bacause &amp;ldquo;PlayStation&amp;rdquo; is my religion (on Facebook, at least :) ).
What happended? I faced the truth - mainstream mobile gaming is already on Android and iOS, and a lot of titles are released every day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on the mobile revolution</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</guid>
      <description>People keep talking about &amp;ldquo;mobile&amp;rdquo;, how it&amp;rsquo;s going to be very important (i.e. &amp;ldquo;we have mobile first policy&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip;) but recently it really struck me: most talking about mobile revolution have abolutely no idea. They just don&amp;rsquo;t get it. Which is a bit sad, actually, especially if you think that big media companies are still struggling to make sense of what to do with classic, web-based Internet. Mobile is a revolution can only be understood by mobile users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Onswipe - entering the era of tablet publishing</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/04/onswipe-entering-the-era-of-tablet-publishing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/04/onswipe-entering-the-era-of-tablet-publishing/</guid>
      <description>Classic web is dying, even if slowly. I will write longer post about that soon. In the meantime, try to use Flipboard for a while … and you will notice that classic portals/blogs are just dinosaurs. They might not know it yet but it doesn&amp;rsquo;t change the facts.
If you are using WordPress, there is a cure called Onswipe. It&amp;rsquo;s not perfect (in fact it is buggy as hell) but shows a lot of promise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is it time to try an Adroid phone now?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/05/08/is-it-time-to-try-an-adroid-phone-now/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/05/08/is-it-time-to-try-an-adroid-phone-now/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been an IPhone user for loong time. While I did not own the &amp;ldquo;1G&amp;rdquo;, I have my 3G for more than two years now. And, to be honest, it begins to show its age. For quite some time, it wasn&amp;rsquo;t getting any of the new cool stuff in iOS, and iOS version 4 actually should have never been released on iPhone 3G because it makes a lot of stuff run noticeably slower.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What to expect from iPad 2</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/01/20/what-to-expect-from-ipad-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/01/20/what-to-expect-from-ipad-2/</guid>
      <description>Before CES, I&amp;rsquo;d say &amp;ldquo;not much&amp;rdquo;. The thing is, today Apple owns the tablet market (if defined as dedicated hardware running dedicated OS), there is almost no competition out there. But it is on the horizon. Take Motorola Xoom as an example. Hardware specs are way beyond iPad 1.0, and if Android 3.0 is going to be that good as people claim, Apple is going to be in real trouble if they release underpowered device.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Apple Tablet</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2010/02/06/apple-ipad-first-thoughts/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2010 11:52:02 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2010/02/06/apple-ipad-first-thoughts/</guid>
      <description>Apple tablet is no longer a mystery. The question now is whether it meets the expectations or fits any real needs :) Basically it is an oversized iPhone - 1024x768 multitouch display, 16-64 GB of flash memory, 1 GHz custom CPU, WiFi, Bluetooth etc, and it runs iPhone OS. I already have an iPhone. Is iPad going to perform better enough to justify buying additional device?
GMail support with push in the iPhone is most of the time sufficient for me.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
