<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Technology on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</title>
    <link>https://maciejmroz.com/categories/technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Technology on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 16:03:03 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://maciejmroz.com/categories/technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Moving the blog to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/11/26/moving-the-blog-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 16:03:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/11/26/moving-the-blog-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Quite a chunk of time has passed since my last update to this blog. While primary reason is my super busy life (on both proffessional and personal fronts) there was also another one I have finally addressed, along with a few extras. The reason was that over the years I simply grew tired of WordPress software. The point to migrate away from it occupied my TODO list for too long. I am not going to bash WP here, I used it for many years, and for that I am grateful to its authors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond virtualization</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2015/01/01/beyond-virtualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2015/01/01/beyond-virtualization/</guid>
      <description>I guess it&amp;rsquo;s time to sum up recent trends in how we build, deploy, and operate complex server side software. Virtualization and cloud computing have been with us for quite a while but right now the era of containers is coming, with entire Docker ecosystem paving the way. You might want to ask a very valid question: &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s in it for me?&amp;rdquo; :) I will focus on business implications of the technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The structure in unstructured data</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/03/09/the-structure-in-unstructured-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/03/09/the-structure-in-unstructured-data/</guid>
      <description>Working with data is something I personally consider one of the coolest things one can do right now in the tech industry. Typically when someone thinks or talks about &amp;ldquo;Big Data&amp;rdquo; it implies petabyte data sets and Hadoop clusters spanning 100+ nodes. The truth is, even a lot smaller data and humbler infrastructure can provide great insights and drive the product/service innovation. To me its really a lot closer to &amp;ldquo;Smart Data&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;Big Data&amp;rdquo; - it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how big your data set is, but how much you are able to do with it, and how quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is virtualization a failure of operating systems?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</guid>
      <description>One thing has hit me while watching of this year&amp;rsquo;s LinuxCon Europe presentations - one of reasons virtualization exists in the first place is operating system inability to properly isolate the applications from each other. Look at it this way: the role of operating systems is abstracting the physical hardware from the applications. And what is the role of hypervisor? Abstracting the hardware from the opertaing system(s) … Which makes the operating system an application running under the hypervisor, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enter the Node.js</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/07/enter-the-node-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/07/enter-the-node-js/</guid>
      <description>The title says it all, but I probably still should paint some background to this article. Imagine a system where you need very high performance, you need it yesterday, and you don&amp;rsquo;t have infinite funds to simply throw more hardware at the problem. Very important component in this system is a web server. Very simple requests, always generated by code (while system in question does not provide data to end users, you can think of AJAX - definitely there&amp;rsquo;s a similarity).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The demise of spinning disks</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/18/the-demise-of-spinning-disks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/18/the-demise-of-spinning-disks/</guid>
      <description>It was quite some time ago when my company started using Fusion-IO (enterprise SSDs) on our database servers. We are happily using them till this day. The great part is that we could scale vertically and leave software layer unchanged. Even better: we still have room for growth, despite getting more users and our application stack getting more and more demanding. We were one of the first to switch to SSDs on server side - so right now it&amp;rsquo;s interesting that this idea propagated so quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you haven&#39;t noticed, OpenGL API is alive and kicking</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/04/if-you-havent-noticed-opengl-api-is-alive-and-kicking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/04/if-you-havent-noticed-opengl-api-is-alive-and-kicking/</guid>
      <description>Recently I somehow found enough time to read &amp;ldquo;OpenGL SuperBible, 5th edition&amp;rdquo;. It was something done purely for fun, just to see how things are looking today for modern graphics APIs. Last time I did any serious graphics programming, OpenGL was slowly dying.
In fact, my M.Sc. thesis used Direct3D as implementation API. I simply had no choice. There was no standard for anything - every single important feature was exposed through extensions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the era of dedicated gaming devices coming to an end?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>Today was the day when PlayStation Vita launched worldwide. I had the chance to play most of the launch games already during GDC Europe last August and I think that both hardware and launch lineup are impressive. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy PS Vita on launch. It&amp;rsquo;s probably a very sad day for Sony, bacause &amp;ldquo;PlayStation&amp;rdquo; is my religion (on Facebook, at least :) ).
What happended? I faced the truth - mainstream mobile gaming is already on Android and iOS, and a lot of titles are released every day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on the mobile revolution</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</guid>
      <description>People keep talking about &amp;ldquo;mobile&amp;rdquo;, how it&amp;rsquo;s going to be very important (i.e. &amp;ldquo;we have mobile first policy&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip;) but recently it really struck me: most talking about mobile revolution have abolutely no idea. They just don&amp;rsquo;t get it. Which is a bit sad, actually, especially if you think that big media companies are still struggling to make sense of what to do with classic, web-based Internet. Mobile is a revolution can only be understood by mobile users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why PC sales are slowing down</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/03/why-pc-sales-are-slowing-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/03/why-pc-sales-are-slowing-down/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of talk lately about how tablets are eating into the classic PC market, that people don&amp;rsquo;t need PCs any more, and how doomed they are. It&amp;rsquo;s true that we are witnessing a decline of the PC platform, and that this trend will only intensify. At the same time I don&amp;rsquo;t believe that right now it has much to do with rapid growth of tablet market. There are many other resons it is bad to be a PC vendor right now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no such thing as best computing device</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/03/06/the-lines-are-really-getting-blurry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/03/06/the-lines-are-really-getting-blurry/</guid>
      <description>The recent releases from Apple (iPad 2 and earlier new laptops) get me thinking a bit about evolution of computing devices and how we actually use them. The past was very simple: loud and powerful desktops, underpowered laptops with short battery life, and feature phones that couldn&amp;rsquo;t really do much. The technology progress changed things a lot.
As desktops and laptops countinued to improve, smartphones were introduced to the world. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell when that happened, but at some point they could do quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
