<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</title>
    <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/tags/vierualization/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <atom:link href="https://www.maciejmroz.com/tags/vierualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Is virtualization a failure of operating systems?</title>
      <link>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://www.maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;One thing has hit me while watching of this year&amp;rsquo;s LinuxCon Europe presentations - one of reasons virtualization exists in the first place is operating system inability to properly isolate the applications from each other. Look at it this way: the role of operating systems is abstracting the physical hardware from the applications. And what is the role of hypervisor? Abstracting the hardware from the opertaing system(s) … Which makes the operating system an application running under the hypervisor, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&amp;rsquo;s think of it from other angle - why are we using virtualization? We are virtualizing applications, and operating system is only a required intermediary. Typical workload of virtual machine is exactly one application (in general case this is one-to-many relationship, because often single application spans multiple VMs). We do this partly to achieve good utilization of physical hardware, but also to achieve isolation at the level close to &amp;ldquo;physical box per every application&amp;rdquo;. Not as secure, but conceptually equivalent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact, this level of isolation is desireable on the desktop, too. VM to run untrusted USB stick? Seems like a good idea, and that&amp;rsquo;s only one of possible use cases. If we are running entire operating system just to run one application, isn&amp;rsquo;t it a waste? What can run under the hypervisor doesn&amp;rsquo;t really have to be a complete operating system. There are projects like Erlang on Xen (&lt;a href=&#34;http://erlangonxen.org&#34;&gt;erlangonxen.org&lt;/a&gt;) or Mirage that seem to skip the OS and talk straight to the hypervisor API - I am not familiar with the implementation details of these projects, but that seems to be general idea. And that makes hypervisor … an operating system. An operating system that opens up plethora of new and exciting possibilities, and one much better fit for todays world - but still an operating system.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>