<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</title>
    <link>https://maciejmroz.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Maciej Mróz Personal Blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 19:53:04 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://maciejmroz.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My Dog Is a Superhero</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2023/08/08/my-dog-is-a-superhero/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 19:53:04 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2023/08/08/my-dog-is-a-superhero/</guid>
      <description>My dog is not really a superhero ;) Still, the title is catchy and Generative AI can make it look like one:
What&amp;rsquo;s even cooler is that we can create multiple variants around this theme quite easily:
These images are all originating from single photo of my french bulldog but were processed using generative AI model (to be technically correct it&amp;rsquo;s a pipeline and not just one model) called Stable Diffusion XL, done using technique called inpainting, which in a nutshell fills the gaps in the image using user supplied mask.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Implementing password storage with Golang</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2017/02/05/implementing-password-storage-with-golang/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 05 Feb 2017 13:17:09 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2017/02/05/implementing-password-storage-with-golang/</guid>
      <description>The common wisdom says: &amp;ldquo;Do not implement password storage on your own&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip; Considering amount of things that can be done wrong, perhaps relying on one of plenty of external providers is the right thing to do :) If you still want to do this, read OWASP Password Storage Cheat Sheet as a first step. After that, read OWASP Authentication Cheat Sheet - password storage and authentication are close layers and most likely you&amp;rsquo;ll be working on both.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Going for simplicity with Go</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/12/27/going-for-simplicity-with-go/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2016 17:03:44 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/12/27/going-for-simplicity-with-go/</guid>
      <description>If you are backend engineer, you probably treat nonfunctional requirements like security, availability, scalability etc. just as if they were laws of physics. And that&amp;rsquo;s good when working on mature, mission critical systems. But what if you don&amp;rsquo;t need all that and want to simply focus on getting something simple but professionally looking out there? Something like MVP/early stage product?
Do you really need microservices, containers, service discovery, load balancers, caches, multiple databases, all clustered and replicated accross multiple availability zones?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moving the blog to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/11/26/moving-the-blog-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2016 16:03:03 +0100</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2016/11/26/moving-the-blog-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Quite a chunk of time has passed since my last update to this blog. While primary reason is my super busy life (on both proffessional and personal fronts) there was also another one I have finally addressed, along with a few extras. The reason was that over the years I simply grew tired of WordPress software. The point to migrate away from it occupied my TODO list for too long. I am not going to bash WP here, I used it for many years, and for that I am grateful to its authors.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beyond virtualization</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2015/01/01/beyond-virtualization/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2015/01/01/beyond-virtualization/</guid>
      <description>I guess it&amp;rsquo;s time to sum up recent trends in how we build, deploy, and operate complex server side software. Virtualization and cloud computing have been with us for quite a while but right now the era of containers is coming, with entire Docker ecosystem paving the way. You might want to ask a very valid question: &amp;ldquo;What&amp;rsquo;s in it for me?&amp;rdquo; :) I will focus on business implications of the technology.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>LTV of a service</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2014/11/04/ltv-of-a-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Nov 2014 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2014/11/04/ltv-of-a-service/</guid>
      <description>A little story today. It goes like this. I drop by one of our teams, and within completely different discussion I get asked this very &amp;ldquo;simple&amp;rdquo; question:
&amp;ldquo;Can we overlay an actual development team cost on top of product revenues so that we know if we are in the red or in the green?&amp;rdquo;
If you haven&amp;rsquo;t noticed yet, there&amp;rsquo;s a flaw in this question. The problem is, it simply doesn&amp;rsquo;t make sense from economic point of view.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Functional programming trojan horse</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/09/22/functional-programming-trojan-horse/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Sep 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/09/22/functional-programming-trojan-horse/</guid>
      <description>All of game server code at my current company is using C++, and we are still starting new projects using existing C++ framework. I gave a presentation on our server architecture a few months ago, available here (it&amp;rsquo;s in Polish, it was local event here in Kraków). After giving the presentation I was approached by a guy (sorry, don&amp;rsquo;t remember the name) who said something like: &amp;ldquo;It&amp;rsquo;s cool you did all that in C++.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>C&#43;&#43;11 Goodness</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/05/04/c11-goodness/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 May 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/05/04/c11-goodness/</guid>
      <description>While most of my programming life used to be centered around C++, nowadays I do not really spend much time with the language at work (other than doing code reviews). I remain big fan of C++. Despite the fact it&amp;rsquo;s not very fashionable language, it is extremely efficient and quite flexible. What&amp;rsquo;s even more important it&amp;rsquo;s continuing to evolve, and it evolves in the right direction. I took some time to try out the C++11 features refactoring small private project, and it really looks good.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The structure in unstructured data</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/03/09/the-structure-in-unstructured-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Mar 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/03/09/the-structure-in-unstructured-data/</guid>
      <description>Working with data is something I personally consider one of the coolest things one can do right now in the tech industry. Typically when someone thinks or talks about &amp;ldquo;Big Data&amp;rdquo; it implies petabyte data sets and Hadoop clusters spanning 100+ nodes. The truth is, even a lot smaller data and humbler infrastructure can provide great insights and drive the product/service innovation. To me its really a lot closer to &amp;ldquo;Smart Data&amp;rdquo; than &amp;ldquo;Big Data&amp;rdquo; - it doesn&amp;rsquo;t matter how big your data set is, but how much you are able to do with it, and how quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Simulating loot based virtual economy</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/01/04/simulating-loot-based-virtual-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2013/01/04/simulating-loot-based-virtual-economy/</guid>
      <description>Just like many others, in 2012 I spent significant amount of time playing Diablo 3. While I enjoyed the experience a lot, playing the game also pushed me to think about its design. What I found most interesting was random loot system and auction house. Because of that, I recently started to think if I can produce simplified model of virtual currency economy in a game with random loot. Now, one very important caveat: I did not try to model Blizzard’s game.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is virtualization a failure of operating systems?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/19/is-virtualization-a-failure-of-operating-systems/</guid>
      <description>One thing has hit me while watching of this year&amp;rsquo;s LinuxCon Europe presentations - one of reasons virtualization exists in the first place is operating system inability to properly isolate the applications from each other. Look at it this way: the role of operating systems is abstracting the physical hardware from the applications. And what is the role of hypervisor? Abstracting the hardware from the opertaing system(s) … Which makes the operating system an application running under the hypervisor, doesn&amp;rsquo;t it?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What can one day of coding bring?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/01/what-can-one-day-of-coding-bring/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Dec 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/12/01/what-can-one-day-of-coding-bring/</guid>
      <description>We&amp;rsquo;ve had our first internal hackaton recently at Ganymede. We don&amp;rsquo;t have &amp;ldquo;20% time&amp;rdquo; rule or anything like that, so the entire thing was a huge experiment. What we did was to take not one, but two days (Thursday and Friday) off our normal schedule to allow people do some cool stuff.Obviosly, because we are a game development company, most teams decided to a game. With all my responsibilities, I did not commit to any team, but decided to do small project on my own - to last minute I did not actually know if I would be tied up in other stuff or not.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Diablo 3 review</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/28/diablo-3-review/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/28/diablo-3-review/</guid>
      <description>After a while of playing Diablo 3 it&amp;rsquo;s probably about time for me to publish my own opinion on the game. A warning: I was never really a Diablo 2 fan (at the time when it was big I was mostly playing a game called &amp;ldquo;Visual C++&amp;rdquo; :) ) so consider it a noob review if you want to :)
Like many people out there, I started out as a Monk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Enter the Node.js</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/07/enter-the-node-js/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/07/07/enter-the-node-js/</guid>
      <description>The title says it all, but I probably still should paint some background to this article. Imagine a system where you need very high performance, you need it yesterday, and you don&amp;rsquo;t have infinite funds to simply throw more hardware at the problem. Very important component in this system is a web server. Very simple requests, always generated by code (while system in question does not provide data to end users, you can think of AJAX - definitely there&amp;rsquo;s a similarity).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What is Agile, anyway?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/04/27/what-is-agile-anyway/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/04/27/what-is-agile-anyway/</guid>
      <description>I was recently confronted with very interesting misconception: that Agile and SCRUM are the same thing. It really got me thinking. First, it means that one must be very careful when using the word &amp;ldquo;agile&amp;rdquo; in software development context. Less obvious: SCRUM is de facto standard agile method today, and very often the only one people know or heard about.
Wikipedia lists 10+ different methods falling under &amp;ldquo;Agile&amp;rdquo; umbrella. It&amp;rsquo;s no suprise because agile manifesto is very vague and does not really tell much (if anything) about the how part.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The demise of spinning disks</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/18/the-demise-of-spinning-disks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/18/the-demise-of-spinning-disks/</guid>
      <description>It was quite some time ago when my company started using Fusion-IO (enterprise SSDs) on our database servers. We are happily using them till this day. The great part is that we could scale vertically and leave software layer unchanged. Even better: we still have room for growth, despite getting more users and our application stack getting more and more demanding. We were one of the first to switch to SSDs on server side - so right now it&amp;rsquo;s interesting that this idea propagated so quickly.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>If you haven&#39;t noticed, OpenGL API is alive and kicking</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/04/if-you-havent-noticed-opengl-api-is-alive-and-kicking/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 04 Mar 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/03/04/if-you-havent-noticed-opengl-api-is-alive-and-kicking/</guid>
      <description>Recently I somehow found enough time to read &amp;ldquo;OpenGL SuperBible, 5th edition&amp;rdquo;. It was something done purely for fun, just to see how things are looking today for modern graphics APIs. Last time I did any serious graphics programming, OpenGL was slowly dying.
In fact, my M.Sc. thesis used Direct3D as implementation API. I simply had no choice. There was no standard for anything - every single important feature was exposed through extensions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Is the era of dedicated gaming devices coming to an end?</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/02/22/is-the-era-of-dedicated-gaming-devices-coming-to-an-end/</guid>
      <description>Today was the day when PlayStation Vita launched worldwide. I had the chance to play most of the launch games already during GDC Europe last August and I think that both hardware and launch lineup are impressive. But I didn&amp;rsquo;t buy PS Vita on launch. It&amp;rsquo;s probably a very sad day for Sony, bacause &amp;ldquo;PlayStation&amp;rdquo; is my religion (on Facebook, at least :) ).
What happended? I faced the truth - mainstream mobile gaming is already on Android and iOS, and a lot of titles are released every day.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Some thoughts on the mobile revolution</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2012/01/07/some-thoughts-on-the-mobile-revolution/</guid>
      <description>People keep talking about &amp;ldquo;mobile&amp;rdquo;, how it&amp;rsquo;s going to be very important (i.e. &amp;ldquo;we have mobile first policy&amp;rdquo; &amp;hellip;) but recently it really struck me: most talking about mobile revolution have abolutely no idea. They just don&amp;rsquo;t get it. Which is a bit sad, actually, especially if you think that big media companies are still struggling to make sense of what to do with classic, web-based Internet. Mobile is a revolution can only be understood by mobile users.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My old demos finally on YouTube</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/10/my-old-demos-finally-on-youtube/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/10/my-old-demos-finally-on-youtube/</guid>
      <description>A friend of mine did something I was too lazy to do for a long time - a YouTube version of our old demos.
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=AWe1SmHWxE4
http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7RbkCS2xtuU
Seems like it was ages ago. I have great memories of these times, and have to admit I miss coding just for the pure fun of it. Commercial software development might be fun (especially when making games) but it&amp;rsquo;s really hard to compare.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why PC sales are slowing down</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/03/why-pc-sales-are-slowing-down/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/12/03/why-pc-sales-are-slowing-down/</guid>
      <description>There has been a lot of talk lately about how tablets are eating into the classic PC market, that people don&amp;rsquo;t need PCs any more, and how doomed they are. It&amp;rsquo;s true that we are witnessing a decline of the PC platform, and that this trend will only intensify. At the same time I don&amp;rsquo;t believe that right now it has much to do with rapid growth of tablet market. There are many other resons it is bad to be a PC vendor right now.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>There is no such thing as best computing device</title>
      <link>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/03/06/the-lines-are-really-getting-blurry/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 06 Mar 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maciejmroz.com/2011/03/06/the-lines-are-really-getting-blurry/</guid>
      <description>The recent releases from Apple (iPad 2 and earlier new laptops) get me thinking a bit about evolution of computing devices and how we actually use them. The past was very simple: loud and powerful desktops, underpowered laptops with short battery life, and feature phones that couldn&amp;rsquo;t really do much. The technology progress changed things a lot.
As desktops and laptops countinued to improve, smartphones were introduced to the world. It&amp;rsquo;s hard to tell when that happened, but at some point they could do quite a bit.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
